Guide to the Mike Cox Accessions
The Wittliff Collections
Mike Cox Accessions
1995-2003
The Wittliff Collections https://www.thewittliffcollections.txstate.edu
Cox, Mike (1948)
UPWC.07008
20 Linear Feet
20 boxes
Multiple accessions from Author, Mike Cox document his wrting career as well as his decades of reviewing books for The Austin-American Statesman.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mike Cox, 2007
Biographical Note
Austin-based author and journalist Mike Cox began donating his papers to the Southwestern Writers Collection/The Wittliff Collections in 1993.
Inducted into the Texas Institute of Letters in 1993, Cox is the author of 22 non-fiction books and hundreds of articles, essays and newspaper columns. A native of Amarillo who grew up in Austin, he sold his first magazine story to The Cattleman in 1964 and has been writing professionally ever since.
In addition to his other writing, for more than 30 years he reviewed Texas-related books for the Austin American-Statesman. In 2010, he received the A.C. Green Lifetime Achievement Award. Over the years, his work has earned numerous other recognitions. His most noted work is a two-volume, quarter-million-word history of the Texas Rangers published in 2008-2009. In 2014, his book Cowboy Stuntman was one of two finalists for a Western Writers of America Golden Spur Award. The same book also was nominated to receive a Will Rogers Medallion from the Texas Cowboy Hall fo Fame. Cox lives in Austin and continues to write.
Scope and Contents
Multiple accessions from Author, Mike Cox, document his wrting career as well as his decades of reviewing books for The Austin-American Statesman. The material includes extensive research for books on the Texas Rangers.
Index Terms
Subjects
Books -- Reviews; Publishers and publishing -- Texas
Subjects (Corporations)
Texas Rangers
- Accession 2007-008
  Abstract
  Material consists of numerous newspaper clippings, correspondence, drafts, galleys and proofs of material written by Cox, promotional materials for books, newsletters, and some notes from early college courses in journalism and photography. Material relates to Texana column written by Cox and to his position at DPS in medial relations. When possible, original file names are used and are indicated in quotation marks. Accession contains 133 photos and 3 color slides. A majority of the photos are of authors and were part of new book announcements. A portion of the material is from Betty Cox whose files consist mainly of correspondence, research notes and drafts, all related to Bob Jamison's book Airplanes, Alligators and Hi-fin Blues.
  - "BC '96" – book announcements, newspaper clippings of books reviews by Cox, and one page of handwritten notes, 1996 (Box 804, Folder 1)
  - "BC 1994" – newspaper clippings, book catalogs, and photocopies of book reviews including some by Cox, and correspondence, 1991-1994 (Box 804, Folder 2)
  - "BC mail" – correspondence dates range from 1989 to 1992 and relate mainly to Cox's Texana column (Box 804, Folder 3)
  - "BC" – articles (including two from Cox) and newspaper clippings, correspondence, 1998-2000 (Box 804, Folder 4)
  - "BC"- articles and biography of Celia Morris, book announcements, correspondence, 2000 (Box 804, Folder 5)
  - "BC Pending 95" – newspaper clippings, correspondence, notes and book announcements (Box 804, Folder 6)
  - "Texas Writers/correspondence from", 1983 (Box 804, Folder 7)
  - "BC 2001/02" – holiday card, Tom Lea keepsake, book press releases, book catalogs (Box 804, Folder 8)
  - "BC 2002" – various book catalogs, book announcements, and correspondence (Box 804, Folder 9)
  - "Texas Publishers Assn." – applications, directories, newsletters and other information on the Book Publishers of Texas (Box 804, Folder 10)
  - "BC" '03" – materials relating to the Texas Book Festival "On the Road 2005", program and tickets to The Dead Presidents Club, and newspaper clippings on variety of books (Box 804, Folder 11)
  - "Texas Writers Press" – newsletter The First Twenty-Five Years, book catalogs, articles on Texas Western Press, and book press releases, 1974-1995 (Box 804, Folder 12)
  - "Book co/mail 1988" – correspondence sent to Cox in regards to his column, subject matter and letters seeking advice on research and writing (Box 804, Folder 13)
  - "Maverick Books" – mainly Hank the Cowdog materials including newspaper clippings, book press releases, book covers, book marks, and articles and information on author John Erickson (Box 804, Folder 14)
  - "Naylor Co." – catalogs and other information from Naylor Company plus a letter proposing James Farber into the Military Collectors and Historians, 1952 (Box 804, Folder 15)
  - "BC '05" – book press releases, newspaper clippings, museum exhibit announcements and an uncorrected proof of A Brave Boy and A Good Soldier (Box 804, Folder 16)
  - "Wind River Press" – a few ephemera from Wind River Press (Box 804, Folder 17)
  - "Pressworks Publishing, Inc." – correspondence from Pressworks and several book announcements including A Texas Christmas by John Edward Weems and designed by Barbara and Fred Whitehead, 1985-1986 (Box 804, Folder 18)
  - "OU Press" – book catalogs and book announcements from the University of Oklahoma Press (Box 804, Folder 19)
  - "Shearer Publishing Co." – book lists, catalogs, and book announcements from the Shearer company, hand written and typed notes by Cox, and newspaper clippings on company, 1987 (Box 804, Folder 20)
  - "Shoal Creek Publishers" – book catalog and book announcements including Jose Vives-Atsara": His Life and His Art by Nancy Glass West, 1976 (Box 804, Folder 21)
  - "Texas Monthly Press" [part 1 of 2] – book press releases from TM Press, 1986-1990 (Box 804, Folder 22)
  - "Texas Monthly Press" [part 2 of 2] – various newspaper clippings, mainly book reviews on books published by TM Press, handwritten notes, Gulf Publishing Co. material, and book catalogs from Texas Monthly Press, 2003, undated (Box 804, Folder 23)
  - "SMU Press/Dallas" – a few newspaper clippings, book announcement and SMU Press: The First Forty Years, a booklet containing remarks by President Zumberge recounting the history of SMU Press, May 5, 1978 (Box 804, Folder 24)
  - "Taylor Publishing Co." – two book announcements, one newspaper clipping and one piece correspondence mentioning Texas Sketches by A. C. Greene (Box 804, Folder 25)
  - "A and M Press" – mainly book announcements and reviews from A & M Press, limited correspondence, book catalogs from 1983, and a price listing of "The Frank H. Wardlaw Collection of Texas Art". (Box 805, Folder 1)
  - Material related to Cox's work with the Texas Author Website. Includes handwritten notes and a list of authors' names and addresses, 1997 (Box 805, Folder 2)
  - "State House Press" – limited correspondence, book announcements, newsletters and catalogs, 1986-1988, 1990s (Box 805, Folder 3)
  - "Still Point Press" – three copies of catalog I, a book list, and two announcements for Al Lowman's book Remembering Carl Hertzog (Box 805, Folder 4)
  - "TCU Press" – mainly book announcements and two newsletters from Texas Christian University Press (Box 805, Folder 5)
  - "Texian Press" – a few book lists and book announcements (Box 805, Folder 6)
  - "Eakin, Ed death 2/20/02" – business files from Nortex Publisher and the Quanah Tribune, book catalogs from Eakin Press, hand written notes and newspaper clippings on Eakin the man and Eakin Press (Box 805, Folder 7)
  - "El Paso, literary" – various book catalogs and book announcements concerning books about El Paso, newspaper clippings of reviews of books on El Paso, and a few pages of hand written notes (Box 805, Folder 8)
  - "David Farmer" – resume from Farmer and a review of his book Stanley Marcus: A Life With Books (Box 805, Folder 9)
  - "Texas Fiction indexed" – numerous newspaper clippings about Texas authors, book announcements and book reviews, 1960-2002 (Box 805, Folder 10)
  - "Fiction, Texas" – various newspaper clippings on Texas authors, a few book announcements, some handwritten notes and limited correspondence (Box 805, Folder 11)
  - "Michael Mewshaw" – Mewshaw's review of Leon Jaworski's book The Right and the Power, letters to the editor, handwritten notes, and an article about Mewshaw, 1980 (Box 805, Folder 12)
  - "Michener, James" – material deals mainly with Michener's life and work, a few book announcements, a short essay by Michener, and the bulletin from Michener's funeral (Box 805, Folder 13)
  - "Billie Porterfield" – reviews of Porterfield's books A Loose Herd of Texans and Texas Rhapsody: Memories of a Native Son (Box 805, Folder 14)
  - "Ken Ragsdale" – correspondence, flyer for the Ragsdale Orchestra, and the booklet by Ragsdale for his wife, My Life With Janet (Box 805, Folder 15)
  - "Spence, Mary Gordon" – handwritten notes, correspondence, and information about Spence (Box 805, Folder 16)
  - "Southwest Vaquero" – "Southwest Vaquero" newsletters from 1982 through 1984 and the "Buckskin Bulletin" newsletter, 1981-1983 (Box 805, Folder 17)
  - "W. Thomas Taylor" – limited correspondence, some hand written notes, and book announcements for several works by Taylor (Box 805, Folder 18)
  - "Book Requests – ltrs sent '89" – correspondence requesting information on the book Indian Wars and Pioneers of Texas by John Henry Brown (Box 805, Folder 19)
  - "Form letter – Advice" – letters to Cox, ranging from 1987 to 1989, requesting information on books reviewed by Cox in his column; others are requesting Cox to read their material and make suggestions (Box 805, Folder 20)
  - "Texas Institute of Letters" – newsletters, newspaper clippings on organization including reviews of Cox work, and a draft of an article by Cox on the TIL, 1983-2004 (Box 805, Folder 21)
  - "TIL 2" – newspaper clippings about TIL including awards and new members such as Cox, and newsletters, 1985-2005 (Box 805, Folder 22)
  - "Virginia Madison" – correspondence between Madson and Wilke 1969, a short biography of Madison, and newspaper clipping of the library dedicated to her (Box 805, Folder 23)
  - "Marcus Stanley" – draft of Cox's article on Marcus, photo and articles on Marcus, 1981 (Box 805, Folder 24)
  - "Metz, Leon" – book announcements, limited correspondence between Cox and Metz, one photocopy of review of Border: The US-Mexico Line by Metz, 1989 (Box 805, Folder 25)
  - "Net info" – several newspaper clippings about the internet, correspondence between Cox and Kevin MacDonnell, 1999 (Box 805, Folder 26)
  - "Richard Jewel 'leak' Media Relations" – newspaper clippings about Jewel and his treatment after he was mistakenly labeled a suspect (Box 805, Folder 27)
  - "Spokespeople/General info" – newspaper clippings on government and media relations and an article by Cox on communication (Box 805, Folder 28)
  - "BC mail" – correspondence received by Cox concerning book reviews and his Texana column, 1986-1995 (Box 805, Folder 29)
  - "BC Pending/'98" – correspondence, newspaper clippings, book announcements, "Paper Persists" article and speech by David Dary about writing on history (Box 805, Folder 30)
  - "BC 99 II" – book announcements, correspondence, newspaper clipping of the review of Larry McMurtry's book Roads, 1999-2000 (Box 805, Folder 31)
  - "Nortex/Eakin" – book catalogs, book announcements, Cox royalty statement 2001, and newspaper clipping on the Austin "publishing scene". (Box 806, Folder 1)
  - "E Heart Press" – book announcements and a photo of author James Hoggard for his book Elevator Man. (Box 806, Folder 2)
  - "Encino Press" – a few book listings and two articles about Bill Wittliff and Encino Press (Box 806, Folder 3)
  - "Madrona Press" – two book listings and two newsletter from MSA (Box 806, Folder 4)
  - "North Texas Press" – book announcements and a newspaper clipping about NTSU (Box 806, Folder 5)
  - "Publishing" – numerous newspaper clippings and some information about publishing (Box 806, Folder 6)
  - "Publishers, Texas & Southwest" – newspaper clippings, Fall 1989 catalog of "Best of East Texas Publishers" (Box 806, Folder 7)
  - "Eakin Press II" – notes, drafts, book announcements, some newspaper clippings, and limited correspondence (Box 806, Folder 8)
  - "Book col. Correspondence", correspondence relating to Cox's Texana column, 1984-1987 (Box 806, Folder 9)
  - "BC 2001" – book announcements from, book catalogs, and one invoice from University of New Mexico Press, 2000-2001 (Box 806, Folder 10)
  - "Anson Jones Press" – newspaper clippings, book list, and bulletin from the funeral of Thelma Rawls Fletcher, "well-know collector and publisher of rare books" (Box 806, Folder 11)
  - "Austin Book Publishers" - book announcements, some newspaper clippings, limited correspondence, hand written and typed notes, and drafts from Cox (Box 806, Folder 12)
  - "Book publishers Texas" – supplement from The Daily Texan about publishers with a picture of Bill Wittliff on the cover, dated 1982; newspaper clippings, and a few book catalogs (Box 806, Folder 13)
  - "Corona Publishers" – draft by Cox about the San Antonio-based publisher, catalogs, newspaper clippings, and book announcements (Box 806, Folder 14)
  - "Creative Publishing Company" – book catalogs titled The Early West and Ride into History (Box 806, Folder 15)
  - "The Eagle and the Raven" – a few hand written notes, and information on the book The Eagle and the Raven by James Michener (Box 806, Folder 16)
  - "BC mail" – correspondence generated from Cox's Texana column, 1982-1995 (Box 806, Folder 17)
  - "Media relations general" – some hand written notes, photocopies and newspaper clippings on media and publicity, handouts and other information on media relations (Box 806, Folder 18)
  - "BC mail '91/93" – correspondence generated from Cox's Texana column, 1991-1993 (Box 806, Folder 19)
  - "University of Texas Press" – book announcements, some newspaper clippings, and a press release folder for Texas by James Michener, notes by Cox (Box 806, Folder 20)
  - "Forever Texas" – Cox grants permission for his work to appear in anthology (Box 806, Folder 21)
  - "LCRA project 9/18/92" – short script for an announcement about the Colorado River Trails, 1992 (Box 806, Folder 22)
  - "LCRA project 6/95" – marketing analysis for the publishing of LCRA's book Historic Colorado River Trails, 1995 (Box 806, Folder 23)
  - "Lockheed / 3-M"- material related to a project to describe Austin, Texas (Box 806, Folder 24)
  - "Lonesome Guv" – short script of Lonesome Dove parody about the governor's race between Ann Richards and Clayton Williams (Box 806, Folder 25)
  - "Lone Star Junction 9/96" – articles printed from the website, handwritten notes, limited correspondence, by-laws of the organization, and information about the website, 1996 (Box 806, Folder 26)
  - "Lone Star Weekly" – letter stating publication on hold, and information on editor's conference (Box 806, Folder 27)
  - "Outdoor Annual '97" – article by Cox for Parks and Wildlife Outdoor Annual, notes, and a letter of agreement, 1997 (Box 806, Folder 28)
  - "Historic Austin" – materials and correspondence relating to the publication of the book by the Heritage Society of Austin, and newspaper clippings about the book (Box 806, Folder 29)
  - "Media Relations How-to's" – workbook from media relations workshop, magazine articles about public relations, and a handbook titled Law Enforcement Public Information, 1994 (Box 806, Folder 30)
  - "Correspondence" subjects include books, publishers and reviews. Some correspondence is from Betty Cox, 1985-1999 (Box 806, Folder 31)
  - "CMT Schools Project 6/98" – Center for Media Training, project addressed special needs of schools in light of such events as school shootings, etc, and some correspondence, 1998 (Box 806, Folder 32)
  - "Big Bend Panorama 5/96" – evaluation by Cox of Kenneth Ragsdale's book, hand written notes, and organizational outline of book, 1996 (Box 806, Folder 33)
  - "Agent (Dupree/Miller)"- correspondence relating to Cox's agent, notes, and article entitled Queen of the Book Deal, Jan Miller (Box 806, Folder 34)
  - "Santa Gets Busted" – short script about Santa and the Texas Highway Patrol for the Christmas play, 1990 (Box 806, Folder 35)
  - "Hollywood" – correspondence relating to the use of the Texas DPS signage, ID's, etc. in a movie, and newspaper clippings on films made in Texas (Box 806, Folder 36)
  - "NBCC" – the National Book Critics Circle directories, 1986/1987 and 1992/1993 (Box 806, Folder 37)
  - "Amarillo Book" – correspondence relating to research for book Historic Amarillo, and a draft of the introduction by Cox (Box 806, Folder 38)
  - "Amarillo book PR 4/100" – newspaper clippings about book, memo about a book signing, and a thank you letter from the Amarillo Chamber of Commerce (Box 806, Folder 39)
  - "Earp, Rob" – correspondence from Earp concerning a novel about the Texas Rangers and includes character profiles and plot sketch (Box 806, Folder 40)
  - "Commanche Trail TXDot STY" – photocopy of article by Cox (Box 806, Folder 41)
  - Stand-off in Texas gallery proofs (2 folders), February 10, 1998 (Box 807, Folder 1-2)
  - Texas Stand-off: Media Relations in a Crisis draft (2 folders) (Box 807, Folder 3-4)
  - Killers and Kooks: Media Relations in a Crisis early draft (2 folders) (Box 807, Folder 5-6)
  - Killers, Crooks and Kooks: Media Relations in a Crisis draft (2 folders) (Box 807, Folder 7-8)
  - Killers and Kooks: Media Relations in a Crisis draft edited by Linda Cox (2 folders) (Box 807, Folder 9-10)
  - Killers and Kooks: Media Relations in a Crisis draft edited by Betty Cox (2 folders) (Box 807, Folder 11-12)
  - "Hot Live to Austin" – Borger News Herald correspondence and articles by Cox, 1971 (Box 807, Folder 13)
  - "Land book project misc." – correspondence, drafts of articles by Cox, and notes about a book of maps from the records division of Texas (Box 807, Folder 14)
  - "Pecos – Texas Highways" – correspondence, notes, and drafts of Cox's articles on the Pecos River (Box 807, Folder 15)
  - "Press card essay" – article by Cox on who gets a DPS Press card (Box 807, Folder 16)
  - "Storyteller" – article by Cox and limited correspondence (Box 807, Folder 17)
  - "Telephone history project indy" – photocopies of articles about phones, copies of comic strips from The New Yorker and an outline for history piece (Box 807, Folder 18)
  - "Texas crude" – articles on review of Cox's book on Texas humor about oil (Box 807, Folder 19)
  - "Texas Scrapbook" – Cox's publishing contract with Honeysuckle Imprint, list of possible book contributors, and an essay titled Elvis and Me by Michael Adams (Box 807, Folder 20)
  - "Texas Highways June 1993 fact checking" – drafts of articles by Cox with corrections, and notes (Box 807, Folder 21)
  - "TMA History article" – draft of Cox's article about Texas Medical Association, some correspondence, and TMA information (Box 807, Folder 22)
  - "Wind 4/27/92" – materials relating to a possible legal case in which Cox might assist, April 27, 1992 (Box 807, Folder 23)
  - "Windsor" – materials relating to the book Austin: An Illustrated History (Box 807, Folder 24)
  - "Wirtz Book" – correspondence, book proposal and information from UT Press website (Box 807, Folder 25)
  - "Yule Fools" – draft of short script The Story of Elfis Presley", and notes (Box 807, Folder 26)
  - "Wordsmiths copy" – drafts of articles plus letter from Wordsmith rejecting Cox's work, 1981 (Box 807, Folder 27)
  - "Booking / TX Highways 3/98" – correspondence, drafts, and notes relating to article by Cox titled By the Book which appeared in the October 1998 issue of Texas Highways, magazine issue included (Box 808, Folder 1)
  - "Co-OP project '97" – lists of authors' names and addresses in the Texas author database, the University of Texas author database, and separate additions by Cox, 1997 (Box 808, Folder 2)
  - "Disaster MS '04 MCL" – draft with hand written notes from Cox's book Texas Disasters (Box 808, Folder 3)
  - "Kunetka, Jim" – three reviews of Kunetka's work and his business card (Box 808, Folder 4)
  - "LBJ bios" – newspaper clippings of reviews of books about LBJ plus a press kit for the book Lone Star Rising by Robert Dallek (Box 808, Folder 5)
  - "Mr. and Mrs. Felipe La Torre" – notes, drafts and article by Cox titled Kickapoos Almost Immune to Change; clipping from the Austin American Statesman, July 1977 (Box 808, Folder 6)
  - "Matthew, Wat" – newspaper clippings about Matthew's life and death (Box 808, Folder 7)
  - "McMurtry, Larry" – newspaper clippings about The Last Picture Show and Lonesome Dove, articles by McMurtry, and articles about Archer City and McMurtry's book store (Box 808, Folder 8)
  - "VF #3 – 20 Photography Information" – pamphlets on photography, newspaper clippings about photography, and notes from Journalism 231- Basic Photography (Box 808, Folder 9)
  - "Literature, general" – newspaper clippings on reading, authors, and American literature; articles and cartoons from the 30th anniversary of the National Books Awards, and notes from journalism class (Box 808, Folder 10)
  - "Lonesome Dove" – quotes from the miniseries, press photo from CBS of Robert Duval as Gus, printout from the SWWC website and other Lonesome Dove websites, and numerous newspaper clippings about the miniseries (Box 808, Folder 11)
  - "More Basic Texas Books" – Texas Books for Every Library list, other reading lists, newspaper clippings by Cox, correspondence, notes and drafts of Cox's work More Basic Texas Books, book catalogs, and book announcements (Box 808, Folder 12)
  - "Writers /Non-Texas II" – numerous newspaper clippings on authors, and information from the Edgar Allan Poe historic site (Box 808, Folder 13)
  - "Texas Writers" – newspaper clippings and announcements of readings including Courage at the Typewriter and Trail of Feathers, both held at the SWWC (Box 808, Folder 14)
  - "Travel Books" – book announcement for Texas Auto Trails and typed notes (Box 808, Folder 15)
  - "Western Art" – newspaper clippings on artists such as Will James and Charlie Russell (Box 808, Folder 16)
  - "The Westerners" – photocopy of article Posses All Over the Place: Publications of the Westerners", from the Spring 1968 edition of The Library Chronicle (Box 808, Folder 17)
  - "Writers" – newspaper clippings on books and authors including Bill Wittliff, and book announcements (Box 808, Folder 18)
  - "Writers II" – newspaper clippings, correspondence and book announcements (Box 808, Folder 19)
  - "Richardson, Dr. Rupert" – newspaper clippings on local historian (Box 808, Folder 20)
  - "Cody Memorial Library" – essay by Jessie Daniel Ames, and correspondence from Southwestern University (Box 808, Folder 21)
  - "Greeting Card Ideas (Betty Wilke Cox file)" – a few hand written notes for captions inside greeting cards (Box 808, Folder 22)
  - "Art, Texas II" – newspaper clippings about Texas artists and Western art and artists, and museum brochures (Box 808, Folder 23)
  - "AWL" [Austin Writers League] – newsletters, some correspondence and a directory, 1985 (Box 808, Folder 24)
  - "Books: Audio" – newspaper clippings about books on tape, 1988-1994 (Box 808, Folder 25)
  - "Texas Books in Review" – newsletter issues, 1983, 1987 and 1989 (Box 808, Folder 26)
  - "Texas Almanac" – promotional material for the Dallas Morning News Texas Almanac, 1984-1985, 1988-1989, and 1990-1991 (Box 808, Folder 27)
  - "Writers / Non-Texas I" – numerous newspaper clippings about authors and book announcements (Box 808, Folder 28)
  - "Slide show technique" – newspaper clippings about audio and visual presentations, informational material on slides and projectors, and notes (Box 808, Folder 29)